A Finding Aid to the World House Galleries records, 1927-1991, bulk 1953-1980, in the Archives of American Art AAA.worlhoug
Archives of American Art
- Artist Files, bulk 1950-1980; 1927-1991; Series 2; 4.6 Linear feet Box 1-6, 11, OV 12
  - Riggs, Ernest, circa 1962 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Rodin, Auguste, 1955-1982 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Rouault, Georges, 1959-1981; 1929 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 9.
  - Rousseau, Henri, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Roy, Jamini, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Rusti, Frida, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Sacharoff, Olga, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Saetti, Bruno, circa 1963 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Salokivi, Santeri, circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Samant, Mohan, 1965-1978 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Santomaso, Giuseppe, circa 1986 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Sanchez, Jose Luis, circa 1955 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Sbisa, Maria Grazia, circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Serra, Juan, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Settignano, Desiderio da, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Severini, Gino, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Sikeliotis, George, circa 1955 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Sironi, Mario, circa 1954 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Sisquella, Alfredo, circa 1953 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Sochos, Antonios, circa 1954 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Spiro, George, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Spyropoulos, Jannis, 1958-1990 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Spyropoulos, Jannis Photographs, 1958-1990 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Spyropoulos, Jannis Catalogues, 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Spyropoulos, Jannis Catalogues, 1962-1979 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 10.
  - Tamari, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Thompson, J. B., 1965 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Thorarinsson, Sveinn, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Tobey, Marc, circa 1962 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Tombros, Michael, circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Torgersen, T., circa 1932 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Tvede, Niels, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Uncini, Giuseppe, circa 1959 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Vaïto, Agathe, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Vasarely, Victor, circa 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 11.
  - Vassilikiotis, Aristotelis, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Velazquez, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Verdi, Lucien, 1953-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Vermeer, circa 1956 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Verona, Maffeo, 1955-1961 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Vieira da Silva, Maria Helena, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Villasenor, Manuel L., 1952-circa 1954 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Villon, Jacques, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 12.
  - "The Violin Player", 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Welch, Livingston, 1961-1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Wikberg, Nils, circa 1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Wolfson, Sidney, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Yoldassis, Dimitrios, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Zabaletta, Rafael, 1949-1957 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Zurbaran, Francisco de, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Unindentified Artists, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Newsletter and Exhibition Catalogue, Biennale di Venezia (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 92.
  - Oversized Photographs, C. F. Daubigny, 1974-1987 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 39.
  - Oversized Art International Article, Jean Dubuffet, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 48.
  - Oversized Clipping and Exhibition Catalogue, Emile Gilioli, 1958-1963 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 9.
  - Oversized Photographs, Mario Negri, circa 1958 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 37.
  - Oversized Photographs, Arnoldo and Gio Pomodoro, 1957-1963 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 9.
  - Oversized Article, Pierre-Auguste Renoir, circa 1947 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 18.
  - Oversized Book Paysages Légendaires, Georges Rouault, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 21.
  - Oversized Catalogue, Jannis Spyropoulos, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 43.
  - Oversized Clippings, Victor Vasarely, circa 1961-1963 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 53.
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalogue, Jacques Villon, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folder 6.
  - Oversized Posters, Emilio Greco, 1956-1959 (Box OV 12)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 12.
- Inventory Records, 1953-1986; Series 3; 0.6 Linear feet Box 6
  Inventory records include gallery stock inventories, lists of art on consignment, and provenance notes. There are rough and final drafts of inventory organized by category, such as Herman Mayer’s personal collection and the Oriental Antiquities collection, in addition to folders on specific items in the World House Galleries inventory organized by the artist's name.
  Arrangement note
  The inventories for collections are arranged chronologically, with the "obsolete" or outdated rough drafts grouped together at the beginning. The inventories are followed by a list of art on consignment, then the item level folders for inventory arranged by alphabetically by the artist's last name. Inventory and provenance notes are at the end of the series.
  - Obsolete Old Mill Farm Collection, circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Obsolete Herbert Mayer House Collection, circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Obsolete Herbert Mayer Collection, circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Herbert Mayer Collection, circa 1966 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Herbert Mayer Collection, 1976-1982 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Oriental Antiquities Collection, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Oriental Antiquities Collection, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Oriental Antiquities Collection, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Art on Consignment, 1967-1976 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Inventory Items, Bertram, Abel, circa 1979 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Inventory Items, Boudin, Eugene, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Inventory Items, Donatello, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Inventory Items, Dubuffet, 1977; 1959 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Inventory Items, Ensor, James, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Inventory Items, Gauguin, Paul René, 1959; 1979 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Inventory Items, Guerin, A. M., 1978 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Inventory Items, Guidi, Virgilio, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Inventory Items, Klee, Paul, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Inventory Items, Kopman, Benjamin, circa 1972-1981 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Inventory Items, Maestro di San Miniato, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Inventory Items, Maillol, Aristede, 1959; 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Inventory Items, Mezerova, Julie, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Inventory Items, Nolde, Emile, circa 1959 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Inventory Items, Rodin, Auguste, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Inventory Items, Stuart, Gilbert, 1957-1961 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Inventory Notes, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Provenance Notes, 1971-1985 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Sales and Purchases, 1956-1987; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Box 6-7, 13 folders
  Records of sales and purchases consist of sales records, financial documentation of accounts receivable or payments owed for sales of artwork, and documentation of Herbert Mayer's purchases, both abroad and within the United States. The sales records include cost and sales price and date from the founding of the gallery in 1953 until several years after it closed. Also found in this series are correspondence, lists of purchases, appraisals, auction catalogs, and printed materials.
  - Rough Draft of Sales Records, 1957-1966 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Sales Records, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Sales Records, 1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Sales Records, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Sales Records, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous Sales Records, 1957-1980 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Accounts Receivable, 1964-1968 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Purchases Abroad by Herbert Mayer, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Purchases Abroad by Herbert Mayer, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Notes for Purchases Abroad by Herbert Mayer, 1956-1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Hugo Grun & Co. Purchases, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - USA Purchases, 1967-1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - USA Purchases, 1978-1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Gifts, 1970-1987; Series 5; 0.6 Linear feet Box 7, 11, OV 12
  This sereis contains documents about Herbert Mayer’s donations to various schools, organizations and programs after World House Galleries closed. Mayer was very generous to his alma mater, Colgate University, and he donated art from the gallery and his personal collection, along with large tracts of land in Maine. Mayer also made substantial donations to other organizations and institutions, such as the Art Students League, Parsons School of Design, and the Stamford Center of the Jewish Community. Files include correspondence, forms and papers about the gifts, photographs, and printed materials.
  - Art Students League, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Channel 13, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Channel 13, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Colgate University, 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Colgate University, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Colgate University, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Colgate University, 1983-1987 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Colgate University, Maine Lots, 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Colgate University, Paintings and Sculptures, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 13.
  - Colgate University, Photographs of Paintings and Sculptures, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Colgate University, Photography Collection, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Parsons School of Design, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Play Schools Association, Inc., 1981-1985 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Stamford Center of the Jewish Community, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - St. Luke's School, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Oversized Annual Report, Colgate University, 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 15.
  - Oversized Poster and Newspaper, Colgate University, 1970-1978 (Box OV 12)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 10.
- Auctions, 1968-1988; 1956-1959; Series 6; 1.4 Linear feet Box 7-9, 11
  This series holds records related to art work sold through Christie's, Parke-Bernet 84 (a division of Parke-Bernet), and Sotheby's auction houses in New York City. Herbert Mayer sold some art through the auction houses while World House Galleries was open and disseminated the majority of his personal art collection after the gallery closed. The folders contain correspondence, receipts, consignment agreements, settlement statements, lists of art available through the auction houses and other miscellanous materials.
  - Christie's, Jewelry, 1980-1988 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Christie's, Oriental Art Sales, 1969-1974 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Christie's, Oriental Art Sales, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Christie's East, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Christie's London, Persian Ceramics, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Christie's London, Persian Pottery, Coins, Sculpture, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Christie's New York, Jade Necklaces, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Kornfeld & Klipstein, 1956-1959; 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Correspondence, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Correspondence, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, African and Other Ethnic Art, 1971-1975 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Retained the original folder title from the collection. Most of the documents are on African Art, but there are also records titled "Miscellaneous - Coptic, Oceanic, Egyptian, Chinese, Indian, Mexican, African, Etc." which contain lists of items from various countries.
  - Parke-Bernet 84, African and Other Ethnic Art, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Antonio Rossellino Terracotta Relief, 1968-1975 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 14.
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Asian Art Sales, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Asian Art Sales, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Claims for Missing Asian Art, 1973-1977 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Furniture and Coin Sales, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Parke-Bernet 84, Michel Elia Sculpture, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Sotheby's, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Sotheby's, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Sotheby's, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Sotheby's, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sotheby's, "The Dream" by Jean Miro, 1984-1986 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Sotheby's, Fernand Leger Tapestry, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Photograph, Antonio Rossellino Terracotta, 1968-1975 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 14.
- Shipping Statements, 1958; 1968-1986; Series 7; 1.4 Linear feet Box 9-10
  Shipping statement files contain customs forms, correspondence, complaints, condition reports, and other documents related to the transportation and shipping of art work. Most of the files track specific shipments of art from locations around the world to their destination at World House Galleries in New York City.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by the country of the shipment's origin, then chronologically by year. There are a few files with the same dates from the same location that actually represent different shipments. order.
  There are a few miscellaneous folders at the end of the series labeled according to the contents of the shipment, such as ceramics, or the approximate timeframe of a trip abroad during which Herbert Mayber bought art for shipment.
  - Denmark, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Denmark, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Denmark, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Denmark, 1969-1976 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Denmark, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Denmark, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Denmark, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Denmark, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Denmark, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Denmark, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Denmark, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Denmark, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Denmark, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Denmark, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Denmark, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Denmark, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Denmark, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Denmark, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Denmark, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Denmark, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Denmark, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Denmark, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Denmark, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Denmark, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Denmark, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Denmark to New York, 1981; 1969 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Denmark to New York, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Denmark, Sweden, Finland, 1958; 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Denmark, Sweden, London, 1983; 1977 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - England, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - England, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Finland, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Finland, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Finland, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - France, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - France, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - France, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - France, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - France, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - France, 1977-1979 (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - France, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - France, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - France, 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Global Service Shipping Company, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Global Service Shipping Company, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Italy, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Norway, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Norway, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Norway, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Norway, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - South Africa, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Sweden, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sweden, 1977-1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Sweden, 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sweden, 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Sweden, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Sweden, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Sweden, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Sweden, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Sweden, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ceramics, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Summer, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - October-November 1975 Trip Abroad, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - April Trip Abroad, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 13)